Finding Aid for the Louis Thurston Nicholas Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
- PROMOTIONAL MATERIALS AND PRESS RELEASES
  - Promotional Materials—Southeastern Regional Ballet Festival, 1964; Van Cliburn Piano Competition; Ernst Toch (Box 385, Folder 11))
  - Promotional Materials—The Music Box by Irving Kolodin—Dec. 1963 and others (Box 385, Folder 12))
  - Promotional Materials—Letter from Congressman Bart Gordon, Dec. 20, 1985 (Box 385, Folder 13))
  - Promotional Materials—Guerry Matthews and the American Sound with photographs (Box 385, Folder 14))
  - Promotional Materials—Alliance for Arts Education Board and Proposed Changes from State Board of Education, 1982 (Box 385, Folder 15))
  - Promotional Materials—Inspiration Point Fine Arts Colony, Inc., Eureka Springs, Arkansas; Source—Music of the Avant Garde, 1967 (Box 386, Folder 1))
  - Promotional Materials—Personal notices sent to L.N. regarding performances (Box 386, Folder 2))
  - Promotional Materials—Personal notices sent to L.N. regarding performances (Box 386, Folder 3))
  - Promotioanl Materials—Places—Boston, Montreal, Chattanooga, others (Box 386, Folder 4))
  - Promotional Materials—Various schools of Music (alphabetical) (Box 386, Folder 5))
  - Promotional Materials—BMI Press Releases; Resume Lorin Maazel and others (Box 386, Folder 6))
  - Promotional Materials—American Institute of Musical Studies; The Graz Experience (1986—1989); Southeastern Music Center, (1984—1986) (Box 386, Folder 7))
  - Promotional Materials—Sopranos and other Singers (Box 386, Folder 8))
  - Promotional Materials—Singers (Box 386, Folder 9))
  - Promotional Materials—Singers (Box 386, Folder 10))
  - Promotional Materials (Box 386, Folder 11))
  - Promotional Materials (Box 386, Folder 12))
  - Promotional Materials (Box 386, Folder 13))
  - Promotional Materials (Box 386, Folder 14))
  - Promotional Materials—Atlanta Symphony Orchestra—, Oct. 29, 1968—Dec. 20, 1973 (Box 387, Folder 1))
  - Promotional Materials—Atlanta Symphony Orchestra—, Jan. 8, 1974—June 28, 1974 (Box 387, Folder 2))
  - Promotional Materials—Atlanta Symphony Orchestra—, Sept. 18, 1974—Dec. 31, 1974 (Box 387, Folder 3))
  - Promotional Materials—Atlanta Symphony Orchestra—, Jan. 7, 1975—March 28, 1975 (Box 387, Folder 4))
  - Promotional Materials—Atlanta Symphony Orchestra –, April 1, 1975—Sept. 15, 1975 (Box 387, Folder 5))
  - Promotional Materials—American Symphony Orchestra—Chattanooga Symphony (Box 387, Folder 6))
  - Promotional Materials—Cincinnati Symphony Orchestra—, Dec. 15, 1965—Aug. 15, 1969 (Box 387, Folder 7))
  - Promotional Materials—Cincinnati Symphony Orchestra—, 1-23-70—June 12, 1974 (Box 387, Folder 8))
  - Promotional Materials—Cleveland Orchestra, Indianapolis Symphony Orchestra, and others (Box 387, Folder 9))
  - Promotional Materials—Indianapolis Symphony Orchestra (Box 387, Folder 10))
  - Promotional Materials—Israel National Youth Symphony, New York Philharmonic, and others (Box 387, Folder 11))
  - Promotional Materials—Norwegian Festival Orchestra, Ravinia Festival, and others. (Box 387, Folder 12))
  - Promotional Materials—Metropolitan Opera Materials, (1983—1989) (Box 388, Folder 1))
  - Promotional Materials—Operas (not in Nashville) (Box 388, Folder 2))
  - Promotional Materials—St. Louis Symphony Orchestra—, Sept. 1, 1971—Oct. 11, 1973 and Poster 1972 (Box 388, Folder 3))
  - Promotional Materials—Saint Louis Symphony Orchestra—, Jan. 15, 1974—September 8, 1975 (Box 388, Folder 4))
  - Promotional Materials—Saint Louis Symphony Orchestra—, April 14, 1970—June 8, 1971 (Box 388, Folder 5))
  - Promotional Materials—Seattle Symphony Orchestra, Springfield Symphony Orchestra, and others (Box 388, Folder 6))
  - Promotional Materials—Washington National Symphony—, sAug. 25, 1964—May 31, 1967 (Box 388, Folder 7))
  - Promotional Materials—Washington National Symphony –, August 31, 1967—Feb. 1, 1971 (Box 388, Folder 8))
  - Promotional Materials—Youngstown Symphony Society—“Great Performances” (Box 388, Folder 9))
  - Promotional Materials—Collections of Noteworthy Reviews and Press Comments Concerning Symphony of the Air (Box 388, Folder 10))
  - Promotional Materials—Whittemore, Lowe,Preservation Hall Jazz Band, and others. (Box 388, Folder 11))
  - Promotional Materials—Charles Castleman,Violinist,Denes Zsigmondy, Violinist, and others (Box 388, Folder 12))
  - Promotional Materials—Aspen Music School (Box 389, Folder 1))
  - Promotional Materials—Brevard Music Center (Box 389, Folder 2))
  - Promotional Materials—Brevard Music Center, Dartmouth Music Program, and others (Box 389, Folder 3))
  - Promotional Materials—Concert and Artists Division Summy—Birchard Company 1964-65 Season (Box 389, Folder 4))
  - Promotional Materials—Florida International Music Festival at Daytona Beach (Box 389, Folder 5))
  - Promotional Materials (Box 389, Folder 6))
  - Promotional Materials (Box 389, Folder 7))
  - Promotional Materials—Vocal and Opera (Box 389, Folder 8))
  - Promotional Materials—Vocal and Opera (Box 389, Folder 9))
  - Promotional Materials—Vocal and Opera (Box 389, Folder 10))
  - Promotional Materials—Vocal and Opera (Box 389, Folder 11))
  - Promotional Materials—Vocal and Opera—Newsletter of the Opera Arts Association (Box 389, Folder 12))
  - Promotional Materials—Vocal and Opera (Box 389, Folder 13))
  - Promotional Materials—Artists (Box 390, Folder 1))
  - Promotional Materials—Artists (Box 390, Folder 2))
  - Promotional Materials—Artists (Box 390, Folder 3))
  - Promotional Materials—Artists (Box 390, Folder 4))
  - Promotional Materials—Artists (Box 390, Folder 5))
  - Promotional Materials—Mats—Alarie—Curzon (Box 390, Folder 6))
  - Promotional Materials—Mats—Davis—Fleming (Box 390, Folder 7))
  - Promotional Materials—Giovanni—I Solisti Veneti (Box 390, Folder 8))
  - Promotional Materials—Mats—Jospe—McFerrin (Box 390, Folder 9))
  - Promotional Materials—Mats—Neal—Rotterdam Philharmonic Orchestra (Box 390, Folder 10))
  - Promotional Materials—Mats—Shaw—Whitmore (Box 390, Folder 11))
  - Promotional Materials—Mats—Unidentified (Box 390, Folder 12))
- PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Photograph—Peabody College Choir, c. 1947 (Box 391, Folder 1))
  - Photographs—Peabody College (Box 391, Folder 2))
  - 322-2807 (Box 391, Folder 615))
  - Photographs—Peabody College—Christmas Program at Demonstration School; Student Teachers at the Dem School; Massek Festival Band early 1940’s; Nathaniel Patch with Student; Prospective Band Leaders (early 40’s) (Box 391, Folder 3))
  - Photographs—Peabody College—Kees Kooper, Mary Louise Boehm, Irving Wolfe; Peabody Choir, 1942; Peabody Vesper Choir; Peabody Cornet Band, early 40’s; Student Teaching at Dem School; Andrew Ponder in early 40’s (Box 391, Folder 4))
  - Photographs—Peabody College—Peabody Chamber Orchestra; Pagliacci 1948; Music Library; Louis Nicholas and Mary H. Gillespie; Peabody Choir, 1947; Peabody College Choir, 1949 (Box 391, Folder 5))
  - Photographs—Peabody College—Music Faculty (early 1940’s); Harold Decker directing July 1945; Juilliard Quartet Dec. 1949; Band Tour, 1949; Johann Harns and Students; Johann Harris and students;Tom Cowan and Vernon Taylor (Box 391, Folder 6))
  - Photographs—Peabody College—Peabody College Orchestra; J. Andrew Ponder conductor, 1942; Nashville Symphony Players; Cornet Section, Peabody College Band (1946); Andrew Ponder and other players; 1942 photo of judges of band contest; Elizabeth Wilfley, harp (Box 391, Folder 7))
  - Photographs—Peabody College—Sally Parker, harp; John Shelton, French horn; Peabody Choir (early 1940’s); Dance Band Fall 1944; Elizabeth Wilfley, harp; Mary Ann Ridley, Peabody Dem School; Peabody Band, C.B. Hunt, directing; Peabody Band (circa 1942); 2 unidentified (Box 391, Folder 8))
  - Photographs—Peabody College—Student Teaching in the Peabody Dem School; Mozart’s Bastien and Bastienne, 1945; Down in the Valley,1951; Music Library; Graduate Students (Box 391, Folder 9))
  - Photographs—Peabody College—Musical Vesper 8/8/65—Dawn G. Whitte, tenor; Dwight Galwood, Bass, Betty R. Durham, Alto, Martha H. Clark, soprano, Louis Nicholas, piano (Box 391, Folder 10))
  - Photographs—Peabody College—Stanley Quartet, Summer 1956 (Univ. of Michigan); Fine Arts Quartet, June 1963 (Box 391, Folder 11))
  - Photographs—Nashville Community Concert; Group of Nashville Symphony Members, 1958; Louis and Sally Nicholas and chorus members (Box 391, Folder 12))
  - Photographs—NATS certificate of Membership Dec. 31, 1950; NATS workshop, Drew University, Madison, N.J., June 5-12, 1952 (Box 392, Folder 1))
  - Photographs—NATS Augsburg College Workshop, Minneapolis, MN, Aug. 24—28, 1953; NATS workshop Boone, N.C., Aug. 16-20, 1954 (Box 392, Folder 2))
  - Photographs—NATS Convention Chattanooga, TN Dec. 1954; NATS Workshop Peabody College for Teachers, August 19-24, 1956; NATS Workshop, Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia, Aug. 19-23, 1957 (Box 392, Folder 3))
  - Photographs—NATS Officers, Annual Banquet, Cincinatti, Ohio, Dec. 29, 1959; NATS !8TH Annual Convention, L.A., California, Dec. 28, 1962; NATS Workshop, University of Colorado, July 19-24, 1964; NATS Workshop, University of TN (Box 392, Folder 4))
  - Photographs—NATS Silver Jubilee Convention Certificate 1969—Photo of Dr. William Vennard; Dr. Berton Coffin and Louis Nicholas (Box 392, Folder 5))
  - Photographs—Edyth Walker; others unknown (Box 392, Folder 6))
  - Photographs—Teresa Orantes, _____Corillo; Chloe Owen (Box 392, Folder 7))
  - Photographs—Mildred Miller, Anna Kaskas, Sylvia Friedrich, Irene Jordan (Box 392, Folder 8))
  - Photographs—Blanche Thebom, Carol Smith, Johana Simon (Box 392, Folder 9))
  - Photographs—Cesare Siepi, Bass; Jerome Hines, Bass; Cesare Valletti, tenor; William Lewis, tenor (Box 392, Folder 10))
  - Photographs—Hubart Mitchell, baritone; William Wilderman, bass; Toshigo Eto, violinist; Burton Garlinghouse (Box 392, Folder 11))
  - Photographs—Anderson and Theodor Bohlman (Box 393, Folder 1))
  - Photographs—Jorge Bolet; Mary Costa (Box 393, Folder 2))
  - Photographs—Evans Davies; Anthony Di Bonaventura (Box 393, Folder 3))
  - Photographs—Rudolph Ganz; Robert Hale (Box 393, Folder 4))
  - Photographs—Arthur Habert (sp?); Nicole Henriot (Box 393, Folder 5))
  - 322-2807 (Box 393, Folder 615))
  - Photographs—Myra Hess; Irma Helen Hopkins (Box 393, Folder 6))
  - Photographs—Marilyn Horne; Jenny Jennings (Box 393, Folder 7))
  - Photographs—Helen Judson; Lily Kraus (Box 393, Folder 8))
  - Photographs—Calvin Marsh; Allison Nelson (Box 393, Folder 9))
  - Photographs—Paganini Quartet; Menahem Pressler (Box 393, Folder 10))
  - Photographs—Ruth Ray; Robert Walter (Box 393, Folder 11))
  - Photographs—Isabel Scionte; Martial Singher and Bill Zauder (Box 393, Folder 12))
  - Photographs—Ruth Slenczynska; Mabel Steele (Box 393, Folder 13))
  - Framed Print (Box 393, Folder 14))
- SCRAPBOOKS, MEMORABILIA, AND OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Photograph—NATS Annual Banquet—Minneapolis, Minnesota, Dec. 1967 (Box 394, Folder 1))
  - PMA Fraternity paddle, signed by members (Box 394, Folder 2))
  - Fraternity paddle, signed by members (Box 394, Folder 3))
  - 1955 NATS banquet photographs (Box 394, Folder 4))
  - Recognition Plaque April 24, 1979 from Students of the Peabody School of Music (Box 394, Folder 5))
  - Recognition Plaque, 1972, from George Peabody College for Teachers (Box 394, Folder 6))
  - Southwestern at Memphis—The Sou’Wester—, September 19, 1930—May 25, 1934 (Box 395, Folder 1))
  - In folder—Sou’Wester April 27, 1934—Louis Nicholas honored by Council in Election (Box 395, Folder 2))
  - In folder—Ladies Home Journal, 1923-1926 (Box 395, Folder 3))
  - This scrapbook contains newspaper reviews of plays and dramatic programs (non musical ), 1930-1945 (Box 396)
  - 3 separate collections (Box 397)
  - Violin, Viola, Cello, Recorder, Harp, Organ Recitals, Joint Recitals, Chamber Music, etc., 1931 –June 1950 (Box 397)
  - Scrapbook –Nashville Community Playhouse, 1937-1942 (Box 397)
  - Complete Set of Programs, “The Off Stage Noise” Nashville Community Playhouse, November 1935-November 1942 (Box 397, Folder 615))
  - This scrapbook contains programs and newspaper reviews of Musical Comedy, Revues, and Light Opera, 1928-1949 (Box 398)
  - Programs and newspaper reviews of Grand Opera and Ballet, 1928-1949 (Box 399, Folder 1))
  - The Nashville Tennessean, Concert reviews by Louis Nicholas, Music Editor and Critic, 1951-1975 (Box 399, Folder 2))
  - This scrapbook contains Orchestra and Band Programs and Newspaper reviews, 1929-1945 (Box 400)
  - This scrapbook contains programs and newspaper reviews of Choral and Miscellaneous Concerts, 1928—August 1950 (Box 401)
  - This scrapbook contains programs and newspaper reviews of Vocal Recitals, 1930—March 1950 (Box 402)
  - Personal scrapbook 1936-42 including biographical information, newspaper clippings, music and other programs (Box 403, Folder 1))
  - 1939 May Festival Program University of Michigan (Box 403, Folder 2))
  - Commencement Courier (Nashville), 1894-1907 (Box 403, Folder 3))
  - Scrapbook of miscellaneous programs and newspaper reviews, 1942—1947 (Box 404)
  - Scrapbook of Orchestral and Band Programs and Plays, 1946-1952 (Box 405)
  - Personal scrapbook, Dec. 4, 1951; 1954-1956 (Box 406)
  - This scrapbook contains reviews from The Nashville Tennessean by Louis (Box 407)
  - Nicholas, Music Editor and Critic, 1951—1975 (Box 407)
  - Sunday Column: THE MUSIC SCENE, (10-21-51 to 8-27-61) (Box 407)
  - Book Reviews, (12.21-52 to 8-20-61 ) (Box 407)
  - This scrapbook contains newspaper clippings from The Tennessean, 1961-1976 (Box 408)
  - This scrapbook contains newspaper clippings from The Tennessee, 1963-1980 (Box 409)
  - 322-2807 (Box 410)
  - This scrapbook contains articles and reviews by Louis Nicholas in The Tennessean (Box 410)
  - This scrapbook contains reviews and programs from the years, 1947 to 1951. (Box 411)
  - Many articles about Louis Nicholas and includes early Programs (1947—1948) of the Nashville Symphony Orchestra (Box 411)
  - This scrapbook contains programs and newspaper reviews of piano and clavichord recitals from, 1928—June 1950 (Box 412)
  - Scrapbook containing programs and newspaper articles from 1951-1954 including programs from the Nashville Symphony Orchestra and Peabody College Music Series (Box 413)
  - Sheet Music—Music by John Duke including “Stopping by Woods on a Snowy Evening” (poem by Robert Frost) and “To my Dear and Loving Husband” (poem by Anne Bradstreet) and others (Box 414)
  - 1973 Saugatuck Douglas Art Club Calendar (Box 414)
  - Commercial Appeal Magazine “Conversation with Allen Tate” (Box 414)
  - “The Fugitives Recaptured”; “Robert Penn Warren: Southerner” February 13, 1977; Newspaper review of Robert Penn Warren’s All the King’s Men, 1946 (Box 414)
  - Musical America, March 25, May 10, 1936 (Box 414)
  - Memphis Musical Journals—Musical Topics, (1901-02) (Box 414)
  - Melody, July 1927 (Box 414)
  - The Billboard, October 13, 1928 (Box 414)
  - Music and Musicians, Devoted Principally to the Interests of the Pacific West, June 1927 (Box 414)
  - Music News (Chicago, Illinois), July 22, 1927 (Box 414)
  - Music Trades, New York, July 16, 1927 (Box 414)
  - The Music Trade Review, July 16, 1927 (Box 414)
  - The Southern Musical Journal, (19031-32) (Box 414)
  - The Tri-State Musical Journal (1928-29); Southern Symphony, (March 1930) (Box 414)
  - Music Catalog—Organ Works of J.S. Bach (Box 414)
  - Sheet Music—“Duke Ellington Fantasy” (Thor Johnson) (Box 414)
  - Poster — Peabody College School of Music (Box 414)
  - Sheet Music “Summer in Town” Boris Pasternak and Sam Ewell (Box 414)
  - The Challlenge— Tennessee Performing Arts Center (n.d.) (Box 414)
  - Newspaper Clippings—Miscellaneous (Box 415, Folder 1))
  - Newspaper Clippings—Obituaries, list included (Box 415, Folder 2))
  - Newspaper Clippings—Concert reviews (mainly by Sydney Dalton and substitutes), 1951-1964 (Box 415, Folder 3))
  - Newspaper Clippings—Reviews by Sydney Dalton, 1960-1964 (Box 415, Folder 4))
  - Newspaper Clippings—Reviews by Alvin S. Wiggers, Sydney Dalton, Henri Minsky, Bliss Wiant, and others, 1944-1955 (Box 415, Folder 5))
  - Newspaper Clippings—Music reviews by others in The Tennessean, 1975-1980 (Box 415, Folder 6))
  - Newspaper Clippings of Reviews (mainly Werner Zepernick and his substitutes), 1964-1969 (Box 416, Folder 1))
  - 322-2807 (Box 416, Folder 615))
  - Newspaper Clippings—“The Music Score” Werner Zepernick, 1965-1974 ( (most reviews herein from March 23, 1972 on) (Box 416, Folder 2))
  - Newspaper clippings—“The Music Score” Werner Zepernick (and other music reviews), 1975— (Box 416, Folder 3))
  - Newspaper Clippings, reviews mostly by Werner Zepernick, 1970-1972 (Box 416, Folder 4))
  - Newspaper Clippings, reviews mostly by Werner Zepernick, 1973-1975 (Box 416, Folder 5))
  - Newspaper Clippings, duplicate reviews by Werner Zepernick, 1965-- (Box 416, Folder 6))
  - Newspaper Clippings, reviews of plays, operas, etc. seen by L.N., 1969 (Box 416, Folder 7))
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings, 1957-1966, including personal notices about (Box 417)
  - Louis Nicholas (Box 417)
  - Two issues of Soviet Life, January and March 1975 (Box 417)
  - This box contains these items: (Box 418)
  - American Academy of Teachers of Singing Membership Certificate (Box 418)
  - Handel’s Messiah, Dec. 1955 (Box 418)
  - Photograph in War Memorial Auditorium, Nashville (Box 418)
  - Diploma Southwestern at Memphis, B.A. degree, June 5, 1934 (Box 418)
  - Photograph of Sigmund Romberg (Box 418)
  - Photograph of Eleanor Everest Freer (Box 418)
  - Photograph of Igo Gorin and notes by L.N. (Box 418)
  - State of Tennessee’s Outstanding Achievement Award, Oct. 22, 1990 (Box 418)
  - Fraternity paddle with signatures (Box 418)
  - Phi Mu Alpha Sinfonia Fraternity of America—, June 10, 1955 (Box 418)
  - NATS Certificate—Sept. 20, 1960—American Institute of Vocal Pedagogy (Box 418)
  - Community Concerts Tribute to L.N., Oct. 22, 1990 (Box 418)
  - Festival Program—Piano aux Jacobins, 1987 (Box 418)
  - Scrapbook—A Tribute to Louis Nicholas Upon the Occasion of His Retirement, School of Music, George Peabody College for Teachers, April 29, 1979 (includes letters of tribute from students and colleagues) (Box 419, Folder 1))
  - Oversize photographs of NATS conventions—, 1966, 1957, 1958, 1959, 1963 (Box 420)
  - Poster—American Academy of Teachers of Singing (Box 420)
  - Framed photograph—Messiah by Handel, War Memorial Auditorium, Nashville (Box 420)
  - Tennessee, Dec. 9, 1956 (Box 420)
  - Framed cartoon (Box 420)
  - THOR JOHNSON—Tribute from Earlham College, April 20, 1958 (Box 420)
  - THOR JOHNSON—Tribute from the Nashville Youth Symphony, May 12, 1972 (Box 420)
  - Scrapbook containing: (Box 421, Folder 1))
  - Biographical notes on Mrs. Clare Elby (1889-1984) and the programs in her program scrapbook, (1906- 1926) (Box 421)
  - ----Envelope of musician photographs (Box 421)
  - ----Letters and photographs of musicians and artists (Box 421)
  - Scrapbook containing programs, announcements, articles and music of operas, plays, concerts, etc. (Box 421, Folder 2))
  - Scrapbook containing Ursula McCampbell’s programs of European Tours—, summer 1927, 1928 (Box 421, Folder 3))
  - Scrapbook—1930’s—Programs and newspaper reviews about Hume Fogg High School Drama Club presentations (Box 422, Folder 1))
  - Scrapbook—1930-1937—programs and newspaper articles mostly about Southwestern at Memphis (Box 422, Folder 2))
  - Diaries—, 1926-1932 (Box 423, Folder 1))
  - Datebooks—, 1931—1938 (Box 423, Folder 2))
  - This box contains Personal Diaries (1931-1936) of Louis Nicholas with this instruction: (Box 423)
  - “These diaries are being given to the Archives division of the Jean and Alexander Heard Library of Vanderbilt University. This box is not to be opened until my death. (Box 423)
  - --Louis Nicholas”, (4/4/94) (Box 424)
  - Envelopes (Box 425)